A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests, Series E FA314
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Colonial Williamsburg
  - Colonial Williamsburg - By-Laws - Certificates of Incorporation, 1928-1952 (Box 166, Folder 1437)
    Printed copies of by-laws, incorporation, minutes, organization report to State Incorporation Commission with amendments and new by-laws. Correspondents include Thomas M. Debevoise, V. Webb, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - By-Laws - Certificates of Incorporation, 1928-1952 (Box 166, Folder 1438)
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts, 1934-1946 (Box 166, Folder 1439)
    List of gifts with donors from John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; report on status of various funds. Correspondents include Kenneth Chorley, A. Kendrew, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Vernon Geddy, Thomas M. Debevoise, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts, 1947-1960 (Box 166, Folder 1440)
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - Larson Resume of Gifts, Copies of Letters, 1935-1951 (Box 167, Folder 1441)
    Review of John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s gifts to 1950; funds provided, income, amount and purpose of gift.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - June 29, 1934-March 15, 1935 Gifts, 1934-1935 (Box 167, Folder 1442)
    Gifts of 15,000 shares of stock.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - British Headquarters Papers Gift, 1935-1949 (Box 167, Folder 1443)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gift of 1747-1783 British headquarters papers.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - Chinese Porcelain Gift, 1936 (Box 167, Folder 1444)
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - Williamsburg Restoration, Inc. Stock Gift, 1940-1941 (Box 167, Folder 1445)
    Gift of stock and demand promissory notes.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - October 21, 1943 Gift, 1943-1944 (Box 167, Folder 1446)
    Rehabilitation and renovation of properties; care of gardens; completion of restoration.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - Blathwayt Papers, 1946 (Box 167, Folder 1447)
    Gift of Blathwayt Papers by John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - December 29, 1947 Gift (Box 167, Folder 1448)
    Endowment gift to finance certain projects and services.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - April 28, 1950-May 8, 1950 Gifts (Box 167, Folder 1449)
    Gift to carry on current and future projects.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - December 22, 1950 Gift, 1950-1953 (Box 167, Folder 1450)
    Cancellation of pledge to purchase Methodist Church and Eastern State Hospital if purchased by Williamsburg.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - April 10, 1952 Gift, 1952-1953 (Box 167, Folder 1451)
    $15,000,000 gift to be paid in 10 years.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - January 1957 John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Gift, 1956-1960 (Box 167, Folder 1452)
    $5,000,000 pledge.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - Liberalization, 1952 (Box 167, Folder 1453)
    Voiding of any conditions attached to gifts previously made for corporate purposes.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - July 13, 1949 Gift, 1949-1951 (Box 167, Folder 1454)
    Report on status of various funds, gift for replacement, high cost of labor, etc.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Gifts - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Gifts, 1945-1950 (Box 167, Folder 1455)
    Gifts of money and stocks.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Minutes and Meetings, 1942-1951 (Box 167, Folder 1456)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. interest in Colonial Williamsburg.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Minutes and Meetings, 1952-1956 (Box 167, Folder 1457)
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Motor House, 1957-1958 (Box 168, Folder 1458)
    Articles in magazines regarding motor house; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. interest. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Kenneth Chorley.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Public Information Department, 1951 (Box 168, Folder 1459)
    Bulletin giving progress report. Correspondents include Holmes Brown, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Reports, 1942-1959 (Box 168, Folder 1460)
    Williamsburg Restoration, Inc. operating loss for 1953; information for 1953 annual report. Correspondents include Phillip Keebler, Kenneth Chorley.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Reports - Reports on Business and Operating Budget, 1942-1951 (Box 168, Folder 1461)
    Report on financial operations; wartime curtailment of activities; schedules of operating summaries.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Reports - 25th Anniversary, 1952-1953 (Box 168, Folder 1462)
    Publication of 25-year report; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. suggestions for revisions; comments on report by President Truman, General Eisenhower, G. C. Marshall, Herbert Hoover, Dewey, and others.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Annual Report of Administrative Officers and Department Heads, 1953 (Box 168, Folder 1463)
    Annual report, with correspondence commenting on various aspects of it. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Kenneth Chorley.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Treasurers Reports, 1950-1951 (Box 168, Folder 1464)
    Consolidated statement of gross income; comparative statement; statements of capital funds. Correspondents include I. Jones.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Trustees, 1943-1958 (Box 168, Folder 1465)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s opinions of trustees, policy; suggested board members. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Kenneth Chorley, Winthrop Rockefeller.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Craftsmen, Inc., 1936-1937 (Box 169, Folder 1466)
    Agreements between craftsmen and Williamsburg Corporation; promotional program; distribution of products. Problems; approval of Colonial Williamsburg Hallmark. Financial reports; reproduction of articles for sale; catalog of a manufacturer of Colonial items; setting up new shops. Correspondents include Kenneth Chorley, B. Norton, F. W. Darling, V. Webb, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, David Rockefeller.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Craftsmen, Inc., 1938-1954 (Box 169, Folder 1467)
    Agreements between craftsmen and Williamsburg Corporation; promotional program; distribution of products. Problems; approval of Colonial Williamsburg Hallmark. Financial reports; reproduction of articles for sale; catalog of a manufacturer of Colonial items; setting up new shops. Correspondents include Kenneth Chorley, B. Norton, F. W. Darling, V. Webb, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Craftsmen, Inc. - Minutes and Meetings, 1936-1951 (Box 169, Folder 1468)
    Board of Directors; John D. Rockefeller 3rd's interest. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Kenneth Chorley, J. A. Upshur, V. Webb.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Galleries, Inc., 1936-1946 (Box 169, Folder 1469)
    Certificate of Incorporation; purpose; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s $1,000 gift. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Inn, Inc., 1931-1937 (Box 169, Folder 1470)
    History, partial list of visitors; accommodations; financial reports; guests' criticisms. Director's salary; landscaping; report on rates and accommodations; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s compliment to manager. Correspondents include Mary Lindsley, Kenneth Chorley, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., J. D. Green, Vernon Geddy, V. Webb, I. Jones.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Inn, Inc., 1938-1957 (Box 169, Folder 1471)
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Inn - Lodge Addition, 1941-1950 (Box 169, Folder 1472)
    Plans for additional accommodations at popular prices; cost estimates; anticipated revenue. Correspondents include Kenneth Chorley, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Properties, Inc., 1939-1940 (Box 170, Folder 1473)
    Real estate and furnishings purchased by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. from Williamsburg Restoration; transfer of stock certificates; gift of demand promissory note to Colonial Williamsburg, Inc. Purchase of additional property, appraisal; agenda, minutes of meetings. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Phillip Keebler, Kenneth Chorley, Vernon Geddy.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Restoration - General, 1937-1954 (Box 170, Folder 1474)
    Financial statement; accounting and auditing procedures; comments on Colonial Williamsburg, Inc. meetings; employees' medical service program; payment for legal services; report on reproduction program. Correspondents include Kenneth Chorley, C. Belknap, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Phillip Keebler, I. Jones.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Restoration - By-Laws and Amendments, 1949, 1952 (Box 170, Folder 1475)
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Restoration - Investments, 1939-1941 (Box 170, Folder 1476)
    Report on invested funds, status of various funds; investment policy.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Restoration - Payments, 1930-1950 (Box 170, Folder 1477)
    Breakdown of funds expended.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Restoration - Directors, 1950-1954 (Box 170, Folder 1478)
    Notice of election; qualifications of board candidates.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Restoration - Authorization to Mr. Woods, November 30, 1927, 1927-1928 (Box 170, Folder 1479)
    General authorization by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to spend "to finance this entire Program, whether it costs three or four or even five millions of dollars," supplemented by more specific authorizations.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Restoration - Jamestown Island, 1928-1932 (Box 170, Folder 1480)
    Attempts of citizens to induce John D. Rockefeller, Jr. or Virginia to buy island and preserve it as a historical monument.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Restoration - Sunday Opening of Exhibition Building, 1935-1937 (Box 170, Folder 1481)
    Opening judged not counter to spirit of the Sabbath.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Demand Notes, 1932-1940 (Box 170, Folder 1482)
    Statement of Williamsburg Restoration, Inc. indebtedness to John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; tendering of note for money advanced by him; preparation of new note; transfer by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. of Williamsburg Restoration, Inc. notes to Colonial Williamsburg, Inc. Correspondents include Philip Keebler, Kenneth Chorley, V. Webb, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Minutes, 1951 (Box 170, Folder 1483)
    Minutes, notification of meetings, agenda, committee reports; John D. Rockefeller 3rd interest. Correspondents include Kenneth Chorley, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Colonel Arthur Woods Correspondence, 1927-1929 (Box 170, Folder 1484)
    Purchase of property, furniture and furnishings; cost of projects; architectural problems; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. suggestions for Williamsburg motto. Hazards from storage of explosives near Williamsburg. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur Woods, Kenneth Chorley, Charles O. Heydt, William A. R. Goodwin.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Colonel Arthur Woods Correspondence, 1930-1934 (Box 170, Folder 1485)
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Tavern, 1928-1936 (Box 171, Folder 1486)
    Certificate of incorporation; services and operations; lease of Rectory and Travis House. Use of taverns and ordinaries in home economics work at college; investment of funds. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Kenneth Chorley, Phillip Keebler, I. Jones, Charles O. Heydt, Vernon Geddy, Duncan.
  - Colonial Williamsburg - Williamsburg Tavern, 1937-1940 (Box 171, Folder 1487)
- Theaters
  - Theaters - General, 1931-1947 (Box 172, Folder 1488)
    Playwrights, producers, theater-groups, various associations to improve American theatre, all seeking Rockefeller aid or participation; most appeals declined. Laurance S. Rockefeller gift to National Variety Artists' Benefit, 1940-1941. Nelson A. Rockefeller gift to Theatre, Inc., 1946. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, W. G. Van Schmus.
    130
  - Theaters - General, 1931-1947 (Box 172, Folder 1488A)
  - Theaters - General, 1948-1955 (Box 172, Folder 1489)
    Playwrights, producers, theater-groups, various associations to improve American theatre, all seeking Rockefeller aid or participation; most appeals declined. Laurance S. Rockefeller gift to Children's World Theater, 1948. Laurance S. Rockefeller offers to take shares in friend's play, play not produced and offer lapsed, 1954. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, W. G. Van Schmus.
  - Theaters - General, 1948-1955 (Box 172, Folder 1489A)
    David Rockefeller offers to take shares in friend's play, play not produced and offer lapsed, 1954.
  - Theaters - General, 1956-1959 (Box 172, Folder 1490)
    Playwrights, producers, theater-groups, various associations to improve American theatre, all seeking Rockefeller aid or participation; most appeals declined. John D. Rockefeller 3rd contribution to American Ballet Theatre, 1959. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, W. G. Van Schmus.
  - Theaters - General, 1956-1959 (Box 172, Folder 1490A)
  - Theaters - General, 1960 (Box 172, Folder 1491)
    Playwrights, producers, theater-groups, various associations to improve American theatre, all seeking Rockefeller aid or participation; most appeals declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, W. G. Van Schmus.
  - Theaters - General, 1961 (Box 172, Folder 1492)
    Playwrights, producers, theater-groups, various associations to improve American theatre, all seeking Rockefeller aid or participation; most appeals declined. John D. Rockefeller 3rd a partner in Rabindranath Tagore production, 1961. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, W. G. Van Schmus.
  - Theaters - San Carlo Company - Maud de Wagstaffe, 1933-1961 (Box 173, Folder 1493)
    "Madame de Wagstaffe" is a crackpot who writes regularly and incomprehensibly.
  - Theaters - Oberammergau Reception Committee, 1923-1926 (Box 173, Folder 1494)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $5,000 to help underwrite venture trying to save Oberammergau Passion Plan; received full return of his money.
  - Theaters - Theatre de lOdeon, 1924 (Box 173, Folder 1495)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $5,000 to help underwrite visit of French troupe to U.S.; venture failed financially.
  - Theaters - Friars Frolic, 1919-1951 (Box 173, Folder 1496)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $650 to Friars Club, 1919-1922; later appeals declined.
  - Theaters - American Shakespeare Festival Theatre and Academy, 1951-1961 (Box 173, Folder 1497)
    Organization set up non-profit festival center in Connecticut; John D. Rockefeller 3rd gave $50,000; honored as founder.
  - Theaters - Actors' Fund of America, 1919-1957 (Box 173, Folder 1498)
    Organized to care for needy performers; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $25,000, 1919; participated in fund-raising drive. Later appeals declined.
  - Theaters - Negro Actors Guild of America, 1943-1953 (Box 173, Folder 1499)
  - Theaters - Everyman Associates, Inc., 1952-1953 (Box 173, Folder 1500)
    Aims to produce classics rarely shown by commercial groups and give profits to charity; appeals declined.
  - Theaters - Neighborhood Playhouse, 1924-1956 (Box 173, Folder 1501)
    Part of Henry Street Settlement; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $10,000 for two years to support actors' school at Playhouse. Proposal that Lincoln Square be the place for the Playhouse. Correspondents include Kenneth Chorley, Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget.
    130.1
  - Theaters - American National Theatre and Academy, 1946-1956 (Box 173, Folder 1502)
    Appeals usually declined. Laurance S. Rockefeller contributed to 1955 Salute to France. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Theaters - American National Theatre and Academy, 1946-1956 (Box 173, Folder 1502A)
    David Rockefeller contributed to 1955 Salute to France. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Theaters - American National Theatre and Academy, 1956-1961 (Box 173, Folder 1503)
    Appeals usually declined. John D. Rockefeller 3rd gift for touring Indian dancers, 1957. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, David Rockefeller.
    Folder 1503A reviewed by KWR, 05/12/2010. Previously restricted items were reintegrated into Folder 1503.
  - Theaters - Actors Theatre, 1923-1927 (Box 174, Folder 1504)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. underwrote $1,000 of equity players' season expenses, 1924-1927. Group trying to produce American drama at reasonable prices. Correspondents include Kenneth Chorley, Arthur Woods, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    130.2
  - Theaters - Church and Drama Association, 1928-1933 (Box 174, Folder 1505)
    Sought to bring religion and drama together by promoting good theater. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $2,500 in 1928, 1929 and 1930. Personalities; conflicts and problems. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, H. E. Fosdick, G. R. Andrews.
    130.3
  - Theaters - Civic Repertory Theatre, Inc., 1926-1939 (Box 174, Folder 1506)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $2,000; 1928; declined later requests. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas B. Appleget.
    130.4
  - Theaters - American Laboratory Theatre, 1928-1930 (Box 174, Folder 1507)
    Non-commercial, experimental theater. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $10,000 toward deficit. Correspondents include Simon Flexner.
    130.5
- Miscellaneous
  - Williamstown Institute, 1923-1939 (Box 174, Folder 1508)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution toward institute of politics. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Raymond B. Fosdick.
    199
  - Julius Rosenwald Fund, 1928-1948 (Box 174, Folder 1509)
    Edwin R. Embree, formerly of Rockefeller office, became president of Fund in 1928; correspondence between Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, Edwin R. Embree. No close cooperation between groups, however. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Edwin R. Embree.
    67
  - Rosenbach Collection - Historic Documents, 1930-1935 (Box 174, Folder 1510)
    Purchase, repair and retention of documents in New York; "Carleton Papers" then transferred to Colonial Williamsburg after John D. Rockefeller, Jr. bought them from Rosenbach. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Kenneth Chorley, Arthur Woods, P. Rosenbach.
    208
  - Burgesses Corps, 1905-1917 (Box 174, Folder 1511)
    Armory Burgesses Corps of Albany, included many influential life honorary members. John D. Rockefeller declined membership in 1905, 1919. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. accepted life membership, 1914 and contributed $250. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. resigned in 1917. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
- Raymond B. Fosdick
  - Raymond B. Fosdick File - League of Nations Library, 1927-1930 (Box 175, Folder 1512)
  - Raymond B. Fosdick File - League of Nations Library, 1931-1932 (Box 175, Folder 1513)
  - Raymond B. Fosdick File - League of Nations Library, 1933-1938 (Box 175, Folder 1514)